Guide to the William R. Pierce Family Photographs 1933-1979
Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, The University of Montana--Missoula
William R. Pierce Photographs
1933-1979
University of Montana, Mansfield Library, Archives and Special Collections The University of Montana—Missoula Missoula, MT 59812 406-243-2053 http://www.lib.umt.edu/asc library.archives@umontana.edu
Mss 547
Pierce, William R. 1933-1996
1.5 linear feet
The photographs in the William R. Pierce collection cover a variety of subjects in Western Montana and Northern Idaho from the 1930s-1970s. Most notable are the images of Fort Missoula, Montana while it was serving as an internment camp during World War II and images of the aftermath of the 1949 Mann Gulch Fire.
Biographical Note
William R. Pierce was born August 13, 1915 in Topeka, Kansas. He earned a bachelor's degree in Forestry at the University of Washington and then worked as a "gandy dancer" (section hand) for the Santa Fe Railway. From there he joined the Border Patrol and worked in New Mexico before being transferred to the internment camp at Fort Missoula, Montana. He then enlisted with the Navy. Pierce earned a Master's Degree in Forest Management from Yale University in 1947. He was hired by the United States Forest Service as a district ranger at Orofino, Idaho then moved on to Thompson Falls and Noxon, Montana. Pierce earned a Ph.D. in Forest Management from the University of Washington in 1958. He taught Forestry at the University of Montana in Missoula from 1955 until he retired in 1981.
William Pierce married Joann Geddes Randall in 1943 and they had two children, Patricia (1944) and John (1948). He died on October 9, 1996 in Gig Harbor, Washington.
This collection contains photographic slides, negatives and prints taken primarily by William R. Pierce, although images from the 1930s were likely taken by another family member. Included are images of Fort Missoula, Thompson Falls, Noxon, and Missoula, Montana. Also included are many images of Montana's Cabinet National Forest back country, several of the 1949 Mann Gulch Fire, and photos of the Pierce family and recreation around western Montana and Idaho. The majority of images in the collection were described by William Pierce or his son John.
The collection also includes a heart-shaped rock carved by a Japanese internee at Fort Missoula and given to William Pierce.
The materials in this collection have been arranged into four series by format.
Series I: Slides, 1942-1979, 0.5 linear feet
Series II: Photograph Album, 1933-1938 and undated, 0.5 linear feet
Series III: Prints, 1942-1960 and undated, 0.4 linear feet
Series IV: Artifact, circa 1941-1944, 0.1 linear foot
Researchers must use collection in accordance with the policies of Archives and Special Collections, the Maureen and Mike Mansfield Library, and The University of Montana-Missoula.
These images transferred from William R. Pierce to his son, John, who donated them to the UM Archives in several accessions.
Gift of John Pierce, 1998, 2000 and 2005
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the online catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search the catalog using these headings.
Pierce, William R, 1933-1996--Archives
Pierce Family--Photographs
Fort Missoula (Mont.)--Photographs
Forest management--Montana--Photographs; Mann Gulch Fire, Mont., 1949$--Photographs; National parks and reserves--Montana--Photographs; Wilderness areas--Montana--Photographs
Montana; Idaho
Photographs
- Slides, 1942-1979; Series I; 0.5 linear feet
  - Dave, Dolores, Evelyn and Jo skiing at Gibbons, Pass, 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/1)
  - Jean and Joann at Diamond Mountain, January 1946 (Box-sleeve 1/1)
  - Walt and Evelyn at Gibbons Pass, Montana, circa 1942-1946 (Box-sleeve 1/1)
  - Evelyn at Gibbons Pass, Montana, circa 1942-1946 (Box-sleeve 1/1)
  - Jo at Gibbons Pass, Montana, circa 1942-1946 (Box-sleeve 1/1)
  - Chuck Smith at Gibbons Pass, circa 1942-1946 (Box-sleeve 1/1)
  - Walt Morris on rope tow at Gibbons Pass, circa 1942-1946 (Box-sleeve 1/1)
  - Evelyn, Dolores, Jo and Lelia at Lookout Pass, circa 1942-1946 (Box-sleeve 1/1)
  - Jo at Gibbons Pass, Montana, circa 1942-1946 (Box-sleeve 1/1)
  - Chuck Smith at Gibbons Pass, circa 1942-1946 (Box-sleeve 1/1)
  - Walt Morris on rope tow at Gibbons Pass, circa 1942-1946 (Box-sleeve 1/1)
  - Evelyn, Dolores, Jo and Lelia at Lookout Pass, circa 1942-1946 (Box-sleeve 1/1)
  - Lookout Pass ski lodge, circa 1942-1946 (Box-sleeve 1/1)
  - Scenic view of mountains in the spring, 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/1)
  - Wedding car, circa 1942-1946 (Box-sleeve 1/1)
  - Wedding church, circa 1942-1946 (Box-sleeve 1/1)
  - Wedding guests, circa 1942-1946 (Box-sleeve 1/1)
  - Wedding car, circa 1942-1946 (Box-sleeve 1/1)
  - Winter scene, Bitterroot River near Fort Missoula, 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/2)
  - Horse named Pepper at Lolo Peak, Montana, Summer 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/2)
  - Convertible outside of Missoula, Montana, Spring 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/2)
  - Jo with car and Christmas tree, December 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/2)
  - Mann Gulch Fire from Willow Mountain, August 1949 (Box-sleeve 1/2)
  - Mann Gulch Fire from Willow Mountain, August 1949 (Box-sleeve 1/2)
  - Mann Gulch fire camp, August 1949 (Box-sleeve 1/2)
  - Missouri River Gates of the Mountains tour boat, August 1949 (Box-sleeve 1/2)
  - Mann Gulch Fire from Willow Mountain, August 1949 (Box-sleeve 1/2)
  - Mann Gulch Fire from Willow Mountain, August 1949 (Box-sleeve 1/2)
  - Mann Gulch Fire from Willow Mountain, August 1949 (Box-sleeve 1/2)
  - Mann Gulch Fire from Willow Mountain, August 1949 (Box-sleeve 1/2)
  - Fort Missoula detainees, 84-0294, Fall 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/3)
  - Fort Missoula detainees and guard, 84-0297, Fall 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/3)
  - Fort Missoula detainees, undated (Box-sleeve 1/3)
  - Fort Missoula, new arrivals, Fall 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/3)
  - Fort Missoula, Officer's Row in winter, Winter 1941-42 (Box-sleeve 1/3)
  - Fort Missoula in winter, 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/3)
  - Fort Missoula, detention area in winter, 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/3)
  - Bitterroot River in winter near Fort Missoula, 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/3)
  - Bitterroot River and Fort Missoula in summer, 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/3)
  - Mission Mountains and convertible from Highway 93, Spring 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/3)
  - Joann in front of home at Fort Missoula, 1943 (Box-sleeve 1/3)
  - Bill Pierce at Fort Missoula, undated (Box-sleeve 1/3)
  - Bill Pierce in front of home at Fort Missoula, 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/3)
  - Bill Pierce in front of home at Fort Missoula, 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/3)
  - Joann Pierce at Fort Missoula, 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/3)
  - Bill Pierce in front of home at Fort Missoula, 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/3)
  - Joann Pierce in the pool at Fort Missoula, undated (Box-sleeve 1/3)
  - Land at or near Fort Missoula in winter, 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/3)
  - Bitterroot River near Fort Missoula in winter, 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/3)
  - Mountains near Missoula in the fall, 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/3)
  - East from Saint Paul Peak, Montana, undated (Box-sleeve 1/4)
  - North from Saint Paul Peak, Montana, undated (Box-sleeve 1/4)
  - Bull River from Saint Paul Peak, Montana, undated (Box-sleeve 1/4)
  - Engle Peak, undated (Box-sleeve 1/4)
  - The Larson's at Lake Pend Oreille, undated (Box-sleeve 1/4)
  - Joann and Rose with food, undated (Box-sleeve 1/4)
  - House at Noxon, Montana in winter, 1954 (Box-sleeve 1/4)
  - Ranger's house at Noxon, Montana in winter with new addition, 1954 (Box-sleeve 1/4)
  - Car in deep snow, Noxon, Montana, 1954 (Box-sleeve 1/4)
  - Rock Creek Meadows, Montana in spring, 1955 (Box-sleeve 1/4)
  - Rock Creek Meadows, Montana in spring, 1955 (Box-sleeve 1/4)
  - Noxon, Montana group photo, Nancy, Ina, Jean Zimmerman, Pat Joann, John, 1955 (Box-sleeve 1/4)
  - Ducks at Noxon, Montana, July 1955 (Box-sleeve 1/4)
  - Coloma, Montana, 1961 (Box-sleeve 1/4)
  - Active forest fires, undated (Box-sleeve 1/4)
  - Water fall on the North Fork of the Bull River, Montana, 1958 (Box-sleeve 1/5)
  - Cabinet Lake from Squaw Peak, July 1953 (Box-sleeve 1/5)
  - Wildflowers on the Middle Fork of the Bull River, July 1953 (Box-sleeve 1/5)
  - Pack string at Star Gulch, July 1953 (Box-sleeve 1/5)
  - Georgia and Garvin at Squaw Peak; building has been replaced, July 1953 (Box-sleeve 1/5)
  - Billiard Table Peak from Squaw Peak, July 1953 (Box-sleeve 1/5)
  - Ridge of Squaw Peak, August 1953 (Box-sleeve 1/5)
  - Home in Noxon, Montana, August 1953 (Box-sleeve 1/5)
  - Home in Noxon, Montana, August 1953 (Box-sleeve 1/5)
  - Home in Noxon, Montana, August 1953 (Box-sleeve 1/5)
  - Blackwell Lake from Snowshoe Peak, August 1953 (Box-sleeve 1/5)
  - Cabinet Mountains looking south from Snowshoe Peak, August 1953 (Box-sleeve 1/5)
  - Ibex Peak from Snowshoe Peak, August 1953 (Box-sleeve 1/5)
  - Ibex Peak from the Middle Fork of the Bull River, August 1953 (Box-sleeve 1/5)
  - Basin at the head of Bighorn Creek, August 1953 (Box-sleeve 1/5)
  - Bighorn Creek, August 1953 (Box-sleeve 1/5)
  - Blackwell Glacier, August 1953 (Box-sleeve 1/5)
  - Lentz Peak from the north, Cabinet Mountains, Montana, 1954 (Box-sleeve 1/5)
  - Cabin and pack string on Squaw Peak, Montana, 1954 (Box-sleeve 1/5)
  - Saint Paul Lake from above. Cabinet Mountains Wilderness Area, Montana., 1954 (Box-sleeve 1/5)
  - Falls on Rock Creek and Rock Creek Meadow, Cabinet Mountains, Montana, June 1952 (Box-sleeve 1/6)
  - Front view from house at Noxon, Montana, 1952 (Box-sleeve 1/6)
  - Gustafson's going away party, Thompson River, Montana., 1952 (Box-sleeve 1/6)
  - Gustafson's going away party, Thompson River, Montana, 1952 (Box-sleeve 1/6)
  - Saint Paul Lake, Cabinet Mountain Wilderness, Montana, 1952 (Box-sleeve 1/6)
  - Saint Paul Lake, Cabinet Mountain Wilderness, Montana, 1952 (Box-sleeve 1/6)
  - North face of Saint Paul Peak, Cabinet Mountain Wilderness, 1952 (Box-sleeve 1/6)
  - Looking north from Saint Paul Peak, Cabinet Mountain Wilderness, Montana, 1952 (Box-sleeve 1/6)
  - Rock Mountain from Saint Paul Peak, Cabinet Wilderness, Montana, 1952 (Box-sleeve 1/6)
  - Elephant Peak from Saint Paul Peak, Cabinet Wilderness, Montana, 1952 (Box-sleeve 1/6)
  - Moran Basin Lake, Cabinet Wilderness, Montana, 1952 (Box-sleeve 1/6)
  - Bull River from Saint Paul Peak, Cabinet Mountains, Montana, 1952 (Box-sleeve 1/6)
  - Bull river and Saint Paul Peak, Cabinet Mountains, Montana, 1952 (Box-sleeve 1/6)
  - Looking north from Saint Paul Peak, Cabinet Mountain Wilderness, Montana, August 1952 (Box-sleeve 1/6)
  - South Fork of Rock Creek, Cabinet Mountains, Montana, 1952 (Box-sleeve 1/6)
  - Rock Creek falls, Cabinet Wilderness, Montana, May 1953 (Box-sleeve 1/6)
  - South Fork of Rock Creek, Cabinet Mountains, Montana, May 1953 (Box-sleeve 1/6)
  - South Fork of Rock Creek, Cabinet Mountains, Montana, May 1953 (Box-sleeve 1/6)
  - Upper end of Rock Creek Meadows, Cabinet Wilderness, Montana, May 1953 (Box-sleeve 1/6)
  - Wild flowers in the Cabinet Wilderness Area, Montana, July 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/7)
  - Wild flowers in the Cabinet Wilderness Area, Montana, July 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/7)
  - East face of Saint Paul Peak, Cabinet Wilderness Area, Montana, July 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/7)
  - East face of Saint Paul Peak, Cabinet Wilderness Area, Montana, July 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/7)
  - Saint Paul Lake and the East Fork of the Bull River, Cabinet Wilderness Area, Montana, July 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/7)
  - Lower Libby Lakes, Cabinet Wilderness Area, Montana, July 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/7)
  - Libby Creek, Cabinet Wilderness Area, Montana, July 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/7)
  - Upper rock Creek Falls, Cabinet Wilderness Area, Montana, July 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/7)
  - Rock Creek Meadows, Cabinet Wilderness Area, Montana, July 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/7)
  - Rock Lake, Cabinet Wilderness Area, Montana, July 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/7)
  - Rock Lake, Cabinet Wilderness Area, Montana, July 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/7)
  - East side of Rock Mountain, Cabinet Wilderness Area, Montana, July 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/7)
  - Small Lake on Bald Eagle Peak, Cabinet Wilderness Area, Montana, July 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/7)
  - Clark's Fork Valley looking toward Lake Pend Oreille, Idaho, August 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/7)
  - Ibex Peak from the Bull River, Cabinet Mountains, Montana, October 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/7)
  - Pilgrim Creek in the fall near Noxon, Montana, 1953 (Box-sleeve 1/7)
  - Bull River, Montana, October 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/7)
  - Bull River, Montana, October 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/7)
  - Ibex Peak, Cabinet Mountains, Montana, January 1952 (Box-sleeve 1/7)
  - Ibex Peak, Cabinet Mountains, Montana, January 1952 (Box-sleeve 1/7)
  - Picnic at Babcock's, Thompson Falls, Montana, July 1950 (Box-sleeve 1/8)
  - Picnic at Babcock's, Thompson Falls, Montana, July 1950 (Box-sleeve 1/8)
  - Sundance Ridge from Priscilla Peak, Cabinet Mountains, Montana, July 1950 (Box-sleeve 1/8)
  - Moss roses near Pear Lake, Cabinet National Forest, Montana, August 1950 (Box-sleeve 1/8)
  - Blossom Lake Cabinet National Forest, Montana, August 1950 (Box-sleeve 1/8)
  - Pear Lake Cabinet National Forest, Montana, August 1950 (Box-sleeve 1/8)
  - Blossom Lake Cabinet National Forest, Montana, August 1950 (Box-sleeve 1/8)
  - Cooper's Gulch from Burk Summit. Cabinet National Forest, Montana, August 1950 (Box-sleeve 1/8)
  - Steam rising from Thompson Falls in winter. Thompson Falls, Montana, January 1950 (Box-sleeve 1/8)
  - George West's place. Snowy meadow and mountains near Thompson Falls, Montana, January 1950 (Box-sleeve 1/8)
  - Ranger's house in winter. Thompson Falls, Montana, 1950 (Box-sleeve 1/8)
  - Snowy road and fence, Thompson Falls, Montana, undated (Box-sleeve 1/8)
  - Noxon District, high mountain peaks and ridges, Montana, undated (Box-sleeve 1/8)
  - Noxon District, high mountain peaks and ridges, Montana, undated (Box-sleeve 1/8)
  - Rock Creek Meadows, Cabinet Wilderness Area, Montana, May 1953 (Box-sleeve 1/8)
  - Cabinet Gorge dam site, Clark Fork River, Montana, June 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/8)
  - Cabinet Gorge looking upstream from the dam site, Clark Fork River, Montana, June 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/8)
  - Bull River, looking towards the East Fork drainage. Cabinet Mountains, Montana, June 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/8)
  - Berray Bench, Bull River, Cabinet Mountains, Montana, June 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/8)
  - H.J. McGee and Ron Pierce (?) at Seeley Lake, Montana, 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/9)
  - Seeley Lake, Montana, 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/9)
  - Jo in a canoe on Seeley Lake, Montana, 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/9)
  - Shore and islands on Flathead Lake, Montana, 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/9)
  - Bringing in the Christmas Tree, 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/9)
  - Cherry Lake basin in the Cabinet Mountains National Forest, Montana, July 1949 (Box-sleeve 1/9)
  - Bill Pierce on his horse, Humphrey, near the Cabinet National Forest fire lookout, August 1949 (Box-sleeve 1/9)
  - Fire lookout tower in the Cabinet National Forest, Montana, August 1949 (Box-sleeve 1/9)
  - View of the Clark Fork River from Cabinet Mountain fire lookout, August 1949 (Box-sleeve 1/9)
  - Clark Fork river Valley from Clark's Peak, Montana, August 1949 (Box-sleeve 1/9)
  - Cabinet Lake in the Cabinet National Forest, Montana, August 1949 (Box-sleeve 1/9)
  - Irv on Cabinet Lake in the Cabinet National Forest, Montana, August 1949 (Box-sleeve 1/9)
  - Cabinet Lake in the Cabinet National Forest, Montana, August 1949 (Box-sleeve 1/9)
  - Sunset from Cougar Peak, Cabinet National Forest, Montana, August 1949 (Box-sleeve 1/9)
  - Sunset from Vermillion Peak, Cabinet National Forest, Montana, August 1949 (Box-sleeve 1/9)
  - Dam on Clark Fork river at Thompson Falls, Montana, June 1950 (Box-sleeve 1/9)
  - Looking east from Koo Koo-Sint ridge, Cabinet National Forest, Montana, June 1950 (Box-sleeve 1/9)
  - Thompson Falls, Montana, from Clark's Peak, Cabinet National Forest, June 1950 (Box-sleeve 1/9)
  - Bear grass at Priscilla Peak, Cabinet National Forest, Montana, June 1950 (Box-sleeve 1/9)
  - Lewiston and Clarkston, Idaho, March 1946 (Box-sleeve 1/10)
  - Black Mountain from Dull Axe Road, March 1946 (Box-sleeve 1/10)
  - Fording Little Beaver Creek with a truck. Likely near Noxon, Montana, July 1946 (Box-sleeve 1/10)
  - Moose Mountain crags from Deadwood Ridge, possibly in Idaho west of the Montana-Idaho border near Lake Pend Oreille, July 1946 (Box-sleeve 1/10)
  - View from Hoodoo Summit on the Montana-Idaho border near Superior, Montana, July 1946 (Box-sleeve 1/10)
  - Prograde Campground, possibly located in central Idaho, July 1946 (Box-sleeve 1/10)
  - North Fork of the Clearwater River at Cedars Campground, Idaho, July 1946 (Box-sleeve 1/10)
  - Salmon River country, Idaho, August 1946 (Box-sleeve 1/10)
  - Salmon River valley, Idaho, August 1946 (Box-sleeve 1/10)
  - Moose Mountain crags, Idaho, June 1947 (Box-sleeve 1/10)
  - Civilian Conservation Corps (C.C.C.) Camp 184 in Idaho, June 1947 (Box-sleeve 1/10)
  - Rainbow over Civilian Conservation Corps (C.C.C.) Camp 184 in Idaho, July 1947 (Box-sleeve 1/10)
  - Boys of Civilian Conservation Corps (C.C.C.) Camp 184 in Idaho, July 1947 (Box-sleeve 1/10)
  - Moose Creek Valley, Idaho, July 1947 (Box-sleeve 1/10)
  - Sherwin Creek Fire, Idaho, August 1946 (Box-sleeve 1/10)
  - Moose Mountain crags, Idaho, August 1947 (Box-sleeve 1/10)
  - Horse and people at the Nine Mile Remount Depot, December 1947 (Box-sleeve 1/10)
  - Horse and people at the Nine Mile Remount Depot, December 1947 (Box-sleeve 1/10)
  - Lake McDonald, Glacier National Park, 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/11)
  - Cabinet Lake in winter, Cabinet National Forest, Montana, 1954 (Box-sleeve 1/11)
  - Thompson Falls, Montana and valley from Cougar Peak, June 1950 (Box-sleeve 1/11)
  - Fort Missoula in the distance, 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/12)
  - Bonner and Milltown, Montana at the confluence of the Blackfoot and Clark Fork Rivers, 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/12)
  - Border Patrol School, El Paso, Texas, September 1940 (Box-sleeve 1/12)
  - Lolo Peak from Fort Missoula, 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/12)
  - Greenough Valley, Montana, 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/12)
  - Two sawyers operating a power saw in Preacher's Gulch, North Fork of the Clearwater, Idaho, August 1946 (Box-sleeve 1/12)
  - Building a landing at Camp 14, North Fork of the Clearwater, Idaho, December 1947 (Box-sleeve 1/12)
  - Bucking with a power saw at Preacher's Gulch, North Fork of the Clearwater, Idaho, August 1946 (Box-sleeve 1/12)
  - 1st Presbyterian Church, Missoula, September 1942 (Box-sleeve 1/12)
  - Joann Pierce on Hoodoo Summit, Montana-Idaho border, July 1946 (Box-sleeve 1/12)
  - Unidentified hillside and mountains in the Noxon Ranger district, Montana, 1953 (Box-sleeve 1/12)
  - Unidentified hillside and mountains in the Noxon Ranger district, Montana, 1952 (Box-sleeve 1/12)
  - Blossom Lake, Cabinet National Forest, Montana, August 1950 (Box-sleeve 1/12)
  - Frozen water tank at Thompson Falls, Montana, January 1950 (Box-sleeve 1/12)
  - Unidentified forestry and Flathead Valley slides (seven slides), 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/13)
  - Lochsa Lodge in winter (two slides), 1972 (Box-sleeve 1/13)
  - Forestry field trip with Dr. Pierce (six slides), 1979 (Box-sleeve 1/13)
  - Wide view of Thompson Falls, Montana and the Clark Fork River valley, 1950 (Box-sleeve 1/14)
  - Looking east towards Noxon, Montana from Squaw Peak, no called Ch-paa-qn Peak, 1953 (Box-sleeve 1/14)
  - Dam on Clark Fork River at Thompson Falls, Montana, 1950 (Box-sleeve 1/14)
  - Clark Fork River valley from Koo Koo-Sint Ridge, Lolo National Forest, Montana, 1952 (Box-sleeve 1/14)
  - University of Montana school forest, 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/14)
  - Bonner Lumber kiln, 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/14)
  - Bonner Lumber Mill on the Blackfoot River, Montana, 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/14)
  - Logs in the Blackfoot River at the Bonner, Montana lumber mill, 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/14)
  - Log Pond, Bonner, Montana lumber mill, 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/14)
  - Tree planting on Anaconda Company land, Montana, undated (Box-sleeve 1/14)
  - Tree planting on Anaconda Company land, Montana, undated (Box-sleeve 1/14)
  - Tree planting on Anaconda Company land, Montana, undated (Box-sleeve 1/14)
  - Tree planting on Anaconda Company land, Montana, undated (Box-sleeve 1/14)
  - Tree planting on Anaconda Company land, Montana, undated (Box-sleeve 1/14)
  - Train cars full of logs at the log siding at Alberton, Montana, 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/14)
  - United States Forest Service pack animals at the Ninemile Remount Station, Montana, 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/14)
  - Smokejumpers jumping from air plane, 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/14)
  - Visitors inside a United States Forest Service fire lookout, 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/14)
  - Looking through a spotting scope at a United States Forest Service fire lookout, 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/14)
  - Bucking logs with a two-man chain saw, 1951 (Box-sleeve 1/14)
- Photograph Album, 1933-1938 and undated; Series II; 0.5 linear feet
  - Chicago, Alder Planetarium, 1933 (Box 2)
  - Colorado, Garden of the Gods, 1934 (Box 2)
  - Minnesota, 1935 (Box 2)
  - Lakeview, 1936 (Box 2)
  - Texas, 1936-1937 (Box 2)
  - Oklahoma, 1936 (Box 2)
  - New Mexico, 1937 (Box 2)
  - Wyoming and Colorado, 1937 (Box 2)
  - San Francisco, California, 1937-1938 (Box 2)
  - Pinecrest, 1937 (Box 2)
  - Paradise Valley in winter, 1938 (Box 2)
  - Crew, rowing team, undated (Box 2)
  - Logging competition, undated (Box 2)
  - Mount Rainier National Park, Fall 1938 (Box 2)
  - Tacoma Yacht Club, American Lake, undated (Box 2)
  - Del Monte Peninsula, 1938 (Box 2)
  - Border Patrol, undated (Box 2)
  - Fort Missoula, undated (Box 2)
  - Various recreation, hunting and travel photographs, undated (Box 2)
- Prints, 1942-1960 and undated; Series III; 0.5 linear feet
  - Cabinet Mountains, Noxon Ranger District, 1951-1954 and undated (Box-folder 3/1)
  - Centennial, Wyoming, undated (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Diamond Mountain, Salmon Lake, Mormon Peak, 1942-1946 and undated (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Fort Missoula area and internment camp prints, circa 1940s (Box-folder 3/4)
  - Fort Missoula area and internment camp negatives, circa 1940s (Box-folder 3/5)
  - Fort Missoula, Salmon Lake, Clearwater River, undated (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Glacier National Park, Going-to-the-Sun-Road, undated (Box-folder 3/7)
  - Idaho - Orofino flooding, Lewiston, Clarkston, Camp 184, 1946-1948 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - Missoula, Montana, 39th Street, Randall Apartments, 1949-1960 and undated (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Noxon, Montana, 1952-1954 (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Spokane, Washington airport, 1960 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Thompson Falls, Montana, 1949-1951 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Trip from Texas to Misosula, Montana, undated (Box-folder 3/13)
  - University of Montana Senior Forest Camp, circa 1960 (Box-folder 3/14)
- Artifact, circa 1941-1944; Series IV; 0.1 linear foot
  This series consists of a single heart-shaped rock sculpted for William Pierce by Japanese internees held at the Fort Missoula Alien Detention Camp during World War II.